<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Esercizio 8: marcare un testo plain text di circa 3000 caratteri a piacere 
    1 inserire prologo XML 
    2 marcare la struttura usando gli elementi fin qui descritti in particolare marcare 
    tutti i paragrafi usando <p> e la struttura editoriale usando <div> 
    3 verificare che sia ben formato con xmllint ( o xerces con domCounter)
    4 salvare il file XML su github 
-->
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "tei_lite.dtd">
<!--  <TEI> elemento radice  -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader> <!-- intestazione -->
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt> <!-- blocco titolo -->
                <title>The Works of Edgar Allan Poe
                </title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Conversione TEI P5 a cura</resp> 
                    <name>Aurora Baroni</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt> <!-- blocco modo diffusione -->
                <publisher>Project Gutenberg</publisher> 
                <date>19 maggio 2008</date>
                <!-- https://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/25525/pg25525.txt 
                     https://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/25525
                -->
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc> <!-- blocco fonte originaria -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Works of Edgar Allan Poe, Raven Edition</title>
                    <author>Edgar Allan Poe</author>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text> <!-- inizio gerarchia -->

        <front> <!-- materiale che precede il testo (figlio di text) -->
            <p>The Project Gutenberg eBook of The Works of Edgar Allan Poe, The Raven Edition, by Edgar Allan Poe</p>
            <p> This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere in the United States and
                most other parts of the world at no cost and with almost no restrictions
                whatsoever. You may copy it, give it away or re-use it under the terms
                of the Project Gutenberg License included with this eBook or online at
                www.gutenberg.org. If you are not located in the United States, you
                will have to check the laws of the country where you are located before
                using this eBook.
            </p>
        </front>

        <body> <!-- testo codificato (figlio di text) -->
            <div> <!-- inizio struttura editoriale -->
                <head>Volume 2, The Black Cat</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>1843</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>  <!-- marcatura PARAGRAFO -->
                    For the most wild, yet most homely narrative which I am about to
                    pen, I neither expect nor solicit belief. Mad indeed would I be
                    to expect it, in a case where my very senses reject their own
                    evidence. Yet, mad am I not—and very surely do I not dream. But
                    to-morrow I die, and to-day I would unburthen my soul. My
                    immediate purpose is to place before the world, plainly,
                    succinctly, and without comment, a series of mere household
                    events. In their consequences, these events have terrified—have
                    tortured—have destroyed me. Yet I will not attempt to expound
                    them. To me, they have presented little but horror—to many they
                    will seem less terrible than <hi rend="italic">barroques</hi>. Hereafter, perhaps,
                    some intellect may be found which will reduce my phantasm to the
                    common-place—some intellect more calm, more logical, and far less
                    excitable than my own, which will perceive, in the circumstances
                    I detail with awe, nothing more than an ordinary succession of
                    very natural causes and effects.
                </p>

                <p> <!-- marcatura PARAGRAFO -->
                    From my infancy I was noted for the docility and humanity of my
                    disposition. My tenderness of heart was even so conspicuous as to
                    make me the jest of my companions. I was especially fond of
                    animals, and was indulged by my parents with a great variety of
                    pets. With these I spent most of my time, and never was so happy
                    as when feeding and caressing them. This peculiarity of character
                    grew with my growth, and in my manhood, I derived from it one of
                    my principal sources of pleasure. To those who have cherished an
                    affection for a faithful and sagacious dog, I need hardly be at
                    the trouble of explaining the nature or the intensity of the
                    gratification thus derivable. There is something in the unselfish
                    and self-sacrificing love of a brute, which goes directly to the
                    heart of him who has had frequent occasion to test the paltry
                    friendship and gossamer fidelity of mere <hi rend="italic">Man</hi>.
                </p> 

                <p> <!-- marcatura PARAGRAFO -->
                    I married early, and was happy to find in my wife a disposition
                    not uncongenial with my own. Observing my partiality for domestic
                    pets, she lost no opportunity of procuring those of the most
                    agreeable kind. We had birds, gold-fish, a fine dog, rabbits, a
                    small monkey, and <hi rend="italic">a cat</hi>.
                </p>
            </div> <!-- inizio struttura editoriale -->
        </body>  
    </text> <!-- fine gerarchia -->

</TEI>





